Guide to the Biberstein, Bowles and Meacham Records
Biberstein, Bowles and Meacham Records
1944-1954
1944 1954
Biberstein, Bowles and Meacham
MC 00222
This collection contains building plans, specifications, blueprints, contracts, and correspondence from the firm of Biberstein & Bowles, Inc. as well as Biberstein, Bowles & Meacham (later Biberstein, Bowles, Meacham & Reed) of Charlotte, North Carolina. The materials pertain to the construction of the Botany Zoology building (Gardner Hall) and the Print Shop on the campus of North Carolina State College, Raleigh, North Carolina. Documents include building schedules, working drawings, HVAC and plumbing diagrams, design notes, addenda, and superseded plans. A related collection is located in the Special Collections Department of the library at the Univeristy of North Carolina at Charlotte.
Herman "Dick" Von Biberstein (1893-1966) graduated from North Carolina State University with a bachelor's degree in Civil Engineering in 1914. He joined his father's business around this time and from 1915 to 1930 the firm was known as H.V. Biberstein. In 1930, H.V. Biberstein was joined by William A. Bowles and the firm was known as Biberstein and Bowles for the next 18 years. The two men were joined by Louis H. Meacham in 1948, at which point the firm became Biberstein, Bowles & Meacham. It was during this era that the firm designed the Botany Zoology building (later Gardner Hall) and the Print Shop for North Carolina State College, Raleigh, North Carolina.
14.5 linear feet
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Transfer from University of North Carolina at Charlotte, 1991-1993 (Accession no. 1991.0012, 1993.0006).
This collection is organized into two series: DrawingsProject Files
Herman "Dick" Von Biberstein (1893-1966) graduated from North Carolina State University with a bachelor's degree in Civil Engineering in 1914. He joined his father's business around this time and from 1915 to 1930 the firm was known as H.V. Biberstein. In 1930, H.V. Biberstein was joined by William A. Bowles and the firm was known as Biberstein and Bowles for the next 18 years. The two men were joined by Louis H. Meacham in 1948, at which point the firm became Biberstein, Bowles Meacham. It was during this era that the firm designed the Botany Zoology building (later Gardner Hall) and the Print Shop for North Carolina State College, Raleigh, North Carolina.
A related collection, Biberstein, Bowles, Meacham Reed Records, is located in the Special Collections Department of the library at UNC-Charlotte. Only materials relating to North Carolina State University buildings were transferred.
This collections contains building plans, specifications, blueprints, contracts, and correspondence from the firm of Biberstein Bowles, Inc. as well as Biberstein, Bowles Meacham (later Biberstein, Bowles, Meacham Reed) of Charlotte, North Carolina. The materials pertain to the construction of the Botany Zoology building (Gardner Hall) and the Print Shop on the campus of North Carolina State College, Raleigh, North Carolina. Documents include building schedules, working drawings, HVAC and plumbing diagrams, design notes, addenda, and superseded plans. A related collection is located in the Special Collections Department of the library at the University of North Carolina at Charlotte.
Biberstein, Bowles and Meacham; Brabham Robin; Penniger Randy; North Carolina State College--History; Biberstein, Bowles and Meacham; Biberstein, Bowles, Meacham and Reed; North Carolina State University--Buildings--Planning; North Carolina College buildings; North Carolina Raleigh Buildings Specifications; North Carolina 20th century Architectural drawing; North Carolina Architectural firms; North Carolina Architecture 20th century; North Carolina Architecture Designs and plans; Architecture
- Drawings, 1944-1952; 1944 1952
  This series contains building plans, specifications, and blueprints for Gardner Hall and the Print Shop on the campus of North Carolina State University.
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (1 of 6) (Tube 1)
    Raleigh (N.C.)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (2 of 6) (Tube 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (3 of 6) (Tube 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (4 of 6) (Tube 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (5 of 6) (Tube 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building (6 of 6) (Flatfolder 23)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building, 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building, 1950 (Tube 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Approved sketch plans, 1949 (Flatfolder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Architectural plans, 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Blackboard and bulletin boards, 1950 (Flatfolder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Budget bureau, 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 20)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Clark (Bryan) letters, 1950 (Flatfolder 14)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Clark (Bryan) letters, 1950-1952 (Tube 15)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Complaints, 1950-1952 (Tube 16)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Design notes, 1950 (Flatfolder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Electrical (Flatfolder 10)
  - Electrical Plans, 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Equipment layout and structural plans (1 of 2), 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Equipment layout and structural plans (2 of 2), 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Fixtures and painting (Flatfolder 22)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Fixtures and painting, 1944-1952 (Tube 14)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating (Tube 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating, 1950 (Tube 12)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating and ventilating (Tube 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Hanging stone soffit, 1950 (Flatfolder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Job notes and preparation for final report (Flatfolder 13)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Limestone, mo-sai stone and granite, 1951 (Tube 19)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Materials, test data, 1949-1951 (Tube 10)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Mechanical and electrical plans (1 of 2), 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Mechanical and electrical plans (2 of 2), 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Metal doors and frames, 1950-1952 (Tube 13)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Plan data, 1949-1950 (Tube 18)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Plumbing, 1949 (Flatfolder 17)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Reinforcing, 1950 (Flatfolder 18)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Sculptured ornament, 1949 (Tube 17)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Telephone system, 1949 (Flatfolder 19)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Toilet partitions, 1952 (Flatfolder 15)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Unistrut, 1950 (Flatfolder 16)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Ventilation and refrigeration, 1946-1952 (Tube 11)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Design development (Flatfolder 12)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Design development, 1949-1950 (Tube 8)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Design development, 1950 (Flatfolder 11)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop (Flatfolder 21)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop, 1949-1950 (Flatfolder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop, 1951 (Tube 6)
- Project Files, 1944-1954; 1944 1954
  This series contains contracts, correspondence, and notes from the firm of Biberstein, Bowles Meacham regarding the planning and construction of Gardner Hall and the Print Shop on the campus of North Carolina State University.
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Acoustical insulation, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Air conditioning and refrigeration, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Air conditioning and ventilation (1 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Air conditioning and ventilation (2 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Aluminum doors and sills, 1950-1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Anderson (Dr.), 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Architect's final report, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Asphalt tile, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Bids and bidders, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Blackboards and bulletin boards, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Blackout shades, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Brickwork, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Clark (Bryan) letters, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Budget bureau, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Bulletins and addenda, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: CMP materials (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: College engineer, 1949-1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Complaints, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Concrete design mix, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Contracts, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Correspondence, home office, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Correspondence with college and budget bureau, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Credits and extras, 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Credits and extras pending, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Cubage, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Design Notes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Door schedule, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Electrical, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Extras, change orders, and credits from changes, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Final inspection all contracts, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Finish schedule, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Fixtures and painting, 1944-1952 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Flagstone, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Flashing, waterproofing, and roofing, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Foamglass insulation, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Freight elevator, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: General deductions, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: HVB correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Hardware, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Heating and ventilating (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Insurance, builder's risk, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Insurance department, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Job notes and prep for final report, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Keys, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Letters on several mechanical subjects, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Limestone, mo-Sai Stone, and granite, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Louvres, metal, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Materials, test data, 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Metal doors and frames, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Metal pans, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Millwork, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Notes about photographs, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Partitions, moveable, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Plan data, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Plumbing, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Plumbing and heating, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Progress reports, 1949-1952 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Reinforcing, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Reports (1 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Reports (2 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Reports, oversize copies, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Schedule of hardware, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Sculptured ornament, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications (1 of 3), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications (2 of 3), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications (3 of 3), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications, electrical work, contract architect's copy, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications, elevator contract, contractor's copy, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Specifications, general contract architect's copy, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Steel list, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Steel, miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Steel sash, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Southeastern Construction Company, general correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Sunshades, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Telephone system, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Tile and terrazzo, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Toilet partitions, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Unistrut, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Ventilation and refrigeration, 1946-1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Window stools, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Window screens, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Botany Zoology building: Work on 27 months guarantee, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Architecture and plumbing specifications, 1949-1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Design development, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Design development, 1949-1952 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Financial, 1951-1954 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - North Carolina State College Print Shop: Letters and correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 8, Folder 7)